<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the people commonly called Quakers. With some reasons humbly offered to the tender consideration of the members of the House of Commons to incline them to grant the petition of the said People (which they intend to present unto them) that their solemn answers may be allowed without swearing in the courts of Chancery and Exchequer. The said People freely offering and consenting, that if any reputed a Quaker falsify the truth, and by duly convicted theroof, [sic] every such person shall undergo the like pains and penalties as are provided against a perjured person.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18697</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886753</idno>
  <idno type="VID">187739</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264216984</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1130A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.24[86]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide L.7.a.3.[113]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886753</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99886753e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C15:2[86]; B5:2[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the people commonly called Quakers. With some reasons humbly offered to the tender consideration of the members of the House of Commons to incline them to grant the petition of the said People (which they intend to present unto them) that their solemn answers may be allowed without swearing in the courts of Chancery and Exchequer. The said People freely offering and consenting, that if any reputed a Quaker falsify the truth, and by duly convicted theroof, [sic] every such person shall undergo the like pains and penalties as are provided against a perjured person.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:187739:1"/>
            <head>The Case of the People Commonly Called QUAKERS. With some REASONS Humbly Offered to the tender Consideration of the Members of the HOUSE of COMMONS To Incline them to Grant the Petition of the said People (which they intend to present unto them) That their Solemn Answers may be allowed without Swearing in the Courts of <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The said People freely Offering and Consenting, that if any Reputed a <hi>Quaker</hi> falsify the Truth, and be duly Convicted theroof, every such Person shall under go the like Pains and Penalties as are provided against a Perjured Person.</p>
            <div type="case">
               <head>The Case.</head>
               <p>EVer since we were a People it hath been our Principle not to Swear, make or take an Oath in any Case, which HE who is the Searcher of all Hearts knows is no other then purely a Matter of Conscience to Us, and of sincere Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Mind of our Blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, as we really believe and are fully perswaded; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Eminent Martyrs, and Men of holy Conversation, Wisdom and Renown, were of the like Judgement against Oaths and Swearing, in the Gospel Day, and not from any Obstinacy, Disaffection, or Worldly Interest on our Parts, we being really willing and desirous to Answer the Just and good Ends of Law and Government, as a peaceable People fearing God. And for this Cause of not Swearing we have been, and still are exposed to great Sufferings, and extream Hardships in our Persons and Estates, by tedious Imprisonments, Sequestrations and Seizures, which many of us have suffered, and diverse still undergo, tending to our great Ruine; being not admitted by Law, to answer in the Courts of <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Exchequer</hi> without Oath, nor to recover our due Debts, or defend our just Titles, Liberties and Properties from vexatious Suites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>The Reasons.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Our Solemn Declaration or Answer without Swearing may be made of the same Validity as a corporal Oath, and the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sifying thereof Wittingly and Wilfully, as punishable as Perjury it self, and the one is as much <hi>in terrorem</hi> as the other, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Fraud or Falshood: We being also under this Caution, that the righteous God is the Avenger thereof, and will Execute as severe Punishment upon the Lyers as false Swearers, for it is Written in holy Scripture, <hi>All Lyers shall have their part in the Lake which Burns with Fire and Brimstone,</hi> Rev. 21.8, 27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Tho' the Open penalty of Perjury be Reproachful and shameful, (and sometimes attended with a small Fine) yet our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for not Swearing is more heavy, durable, and destructive, by our loss of Liberty, and Sequestration of our Estates; which therefore is an Evidence, that it is really Matter of Conscience to us, and not our Voluntary Choice to suffer such Extremity, because we cannot Swear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The PARLIAMENT Granting an Act for our Relief in this Case, will be a Means to Facilitate the Work of the Judges in the said Courts, for thereby the Merit of the Cause may be judicially searched out, when as otherways we suffer meerly for not Swearing, be our Cause right or wrong.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It will be a Means for all Persons concerned, to come easier to their Rights, without the ruine and destruction of the Party Sued who cannot Swear.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It will prevent ill Disposed and Malicious persons from Vexatious, unjust and chargeable Suites tending to our ruine; And from taking Advantage against us because of our Consciencious Perswasion, in Cases wherein they have no right of Claim upon us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It will disappoint Fraudulent persons, who being prosecuted for Debts at <hi>Common Law,</hi> fly into <hi>Chancery,</hi> where altho their Creditors can Swear, yet joyning a <hi>Quaker</hi> in the <hi>Bill,</hi> tho a stranger and unconcerned in the case, knowing he cannot swear they get Injunctions on purpose to defeat their Creditors of their just Debts.</p>
               <p>We also propose to your serious Consideration, That this Moderation to persons scrupling to Swear, hath had good Effect in our Neighbouring Countries, as above one Hundred Years Experience hath manifested.</p>
               <p>On the 26th. day of <hi>January</hi> 1577. <hi>Guilliaume de Nassaw</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and Statholder of <hi>Holland, Zealand, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">G. Brant's <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the</hi> Low Countries <hi>part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 587. 588.</note> with the consent of the Government and Council, sent his <hi>Mandate</hi> to the Magistrates, commanding (on behalf of the People call'd Menists, who refused to Swear in any Case) That their Yea should be accepted and taken instead of an Oath, they being subject, in case of falsifying the Truth, to the Pains of Perjury.</p>
               <p>In the Year 1593. Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> Son of the former Prince, with the consent of the <hi>States,</hi> gave forth a <hi>Placate</hi> or <hi>Mandate</hi> in behalf of the said <hi>Menist,</hi> to the same effect: Which is observed by all Magistrates throughout their whole Government, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Act of <hi>State</hi> made in the year 1690. In which, next unto the words <hi>Solemn Oath,</hi> are these Words Printed [<hi>As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the</hi> Menists <hi>they shall Declare with true Words instead of an Oath, which shall be holden of the same Effect and value as a Corporal Oath.</hi> So that no difficulty in Determining Controversies, nor Obstruction of Justice appearing by their not Swearing; the same Priviledge is still continued to the aforesaid People.</p>
               <p>And if you please, upon the Consideration of the Premises, to grant the said <hi>Petition,</hi> and Relieve us accordingly, we hope you may live to see the good Effects it will have in this Kingdom, and that it will tend to the Service of the Government, the increase of Trade, furtherance of Justice, and Tranquility of the Subject.</p>
               <p>We humbly Intreat you tenderly to consider this our Consciencious Case for our Relief, as if it was your own, and thereby to Demonstrate your Christian Charity and Compassion, that in being Merciful you may obtain Mercy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>